Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1810-1819., 37 items. (Box-folder 2:3-6)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1819., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 13 July 1819., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
          Questions him [Joseph Story] about an admiralty case concerning the hypothecation of a vessel belonging to the port of Richmond; discusses legal principles of hypothecation in general in the United States; does not think that a piece in the Boston papers should be republished, Mr. [?] Wheaton's appendix; leaves the opinion in the militia case for him [Joseph Story] to write.
        - Joseph Story, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 26 July 1819., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
          Discusses the legal principles of hypothecation and maritime law as he [Joseph Story] sees them in regards to a case in New York, and concludes that the chief-question is "whether the ports of the different states are to be deemed foreign ports in respect to the rights of the hypothecation or of implied lien"; in his [Joseph Story] district, as well as in South Carolina, Maryland, Pennsylvania, and New York, they are; he [Joseph Story] "is open to argument and will follow in a better path. And as the advancement of the law, and not merely of our private opinions should be the great ambition of all judges, I am quite content to yield to the judgement of others."
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia],to Bushrod Washington, n.p., 31 October 1819., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
          Mentions a trial at Richmond for piracy and discusses the lack of international law regarding the same; writes of his subscription to Mr. Bronson's Gazette of the United States which has become the Union.
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1820-1829., 87 items. (Box 2-4)
      - J[ohn] R[andolph] of R[oanoke, Washington, D.C.], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], 6 March [1820?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Discusses constitutional issues involving piracy, the slave trade, and the Supreme Court; mentions [Littleton Waller] Tazewell.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 13 April 1820., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Has not formed an opinion of the case which was remanded to the circuit court of Pennsylvania; congratulates him on the prospect of a full docket in [New] Jersey and upon his empty one in North Carolina; he called on Mr. Blair, the President of the Bible Society, who says he [Bushrod Washington] was a permanent member of the society and in arrears for the years 1816-1819; was frozen on the Rosaline, has scarcely thawed out.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Bushrod] Washington, "Mount Vernon," [Fairfax County, Virginia], 26 June 1820., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Hopes none of the papers of George Washington have miscarried; sent the last ones to him [Bushrod Washington] by a coal vessel of Alexandria; has employed a person to copy the pre-Revolutionary letters of General Washington, and he [John Marshall] will himself copy the military letters in his possession after he [Bushrod Washington] informs him in which volume they will be published; he [John Marshall] will also proceed to copy the letters written between the close of the war and the adoption of the constitution, and has retained no others.
        Including TCy of ALS. 1 page. Including Pst of ALS. 2 pages.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, Mount Vernon, Fairfax County, [Virginia], 2 September 1820., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Encloses an affidavit stating that he [John Marshall] lost the certification meant for T[homas?] Marshall and asks him [Bushrod Washington] to send from Philadelphia a bond to be executed; has received from Mr. Ward of Salem a copy of a letter written by Mr. W[illia]m Fairfax to Capt. Clarke of Salem dated Belvoir 22d. February 1749, which states that "Major Washington [has] just returned from London whither he lately went to get his arrears of pay & be put on the establishment of half pay..." concludes that this cannot be George Washington; poses questions about George Washington's genealogy; asks him [Bushrod Washington] to talk with the editor of Langhornes' Plutarch while in Philadelphia about an anecdote concerning George Washington selling his old charger.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James K[eith] Marshall, "Moreland," near Oak Hill, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 25 September 1820., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Discusses Mr. Moorehead's purchase of Mr. Johnson's land in Fauquier County; wheat and other crops are doing well.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia] to Mr. Justice [Bushrod] Washington, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 7 November 1820., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Describes being thrown by a horse; will bring the letters they agreed to copy to Washington; wishes him to speak again with Mr. Wayne about a second edition of the life of [George] Washington; recommends that Mr. [Mason Locke] Weems have a subscription paper for the letters and life at the same time; thinks they should reduce the charges on the life to half a dollar per volume, then the second volume might be sold for two dollars a volume.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington [D.C.] to Mr. Justice [Bushrod] Washington, n.p., 8 February 1821., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Hopes his [Bushrod Washington] health will improve so he can come visit at the end of the month so they can deliver opinions on various cases including the one from Virginia "which has exerted so much commotion in our legislature" [a case involving an act of Congress allowing a lottery in Washington, D.C. with ticket sales in Virginia contrary to Virginia law. See JK/159l/V5/Rare Book (Virginia)/].
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 26 February 1821. [sic], 26 March l82l., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3:1)
        A letter of James [Keith Marshall]'s informed him [John Marshall] of her return from Chicahominy; hopes that the celebrations of the 22nd did not disturb her too much; Judge [Bushrod] Washington is not well; he [John Marshall] is very busy at Court; dines out frequently and eats too much; does not attend the continual gay parties in Washington. 2 pages. ALS. Including ALS on verso from John Marshall to his son [James Keith Marshall], asking about the health of Jacob, one of the slaves; tells him to purchase as much clover seed as he can if he does not get the money from [?] Smith.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Mr. Justice [Bushrod] Washington, "Mount Vernon" near Alexandria, [Virginia], 15 June 1821., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Hopes his health was not injured by his traveling to Philadelphia to perform his circuit duties; mentions case in his circuit involving merchants indebted to the U.S. on duty bonds; recommends the writings of Algernon Sidney.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 15 June 1821., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Asks his opinion of legalities of a case concerning insolvency and priority of payment to creditors; the Supreme Court opinion in the Lottery case virulently assaulted in the newspapers, especially by Algernon Sidney in the Enquirer who is "supposed to be the champion of the state rights.. .[but] really is the champion of dismemberment;" is anxious to hear if his [Joseph Story] and [Daniel] Webster's amendment to the Massachusetts constitution was approved by the people or not.
      - Joseph Story, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 27 June 1821., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Discusses legal principles of partnership, joint property and the priority of the payment of debts under English and American bankruptcy laws; writes of the federal government; reports on the Massachusetts Constitutional Convention; will send on the next vessel for Richmond some Salem fish and a recipe on how to cook them.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, Alexandria, [Virginia], 13 July 1821., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Thanks him for his opinion on the case on which he [John Marshall] consulted him; has enclosed the letter from Mr. [James] Madison to Genl. Washington which he [John Marshall] had selected last winter but forgot to send; discusses the legal matter of inland and foreign bills and hypothecation relating to the New York case.
        Including TyC of ALS. 1 page. Including Pst of ALS. 2 pages.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 13 July 1821., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Is grateful for his expressions of esteem; hopes the harmony of the bench will never be disturbed; discusses [Thomas] Jefferson's and [James] Madison's doubts of the Supreme Court as the ultimate arbiter of the constitutional questions; comments upon Jefferson's character and influence over the people; encloses Algernon Sidney's essays with their weak argument and violent language; in the Virginian newspapers "not a pen is drawn in support of the sound principles of the constitution of the Union... I look elsewhere for safety."
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 18 September 1821., 4 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Has received the fish and will cook it according to instructions; discusses Mr. [?] Hall and his intended publication of Algernon Sidney's essays and asks if he [Joseph Story] can prevent it; Mr. [?] Caedwell has not yet sent the volume of the debates of the Massachusetts Constitutional Convention; discusses the designs of the Democratic-Republicans in attacking the Supreme Court; questions him about a case involving William McKinly, a tax collector, and his depositions.
      - [John] Wickham, [Washington, D.C.], to [John] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], 25 November [1821?]., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Asks him to join him at dinner on Tuesday at 4 o'clock.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Lyttleton [Littleton] Waller Tazewell, Norfolk, [Virginia], 19 May 1822., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Makes arrangements for his [Littleton Waller Tazewell's] deposition to be taken on 23 May; if General [Robert Barraud] Taylor and Mr. [?] Blair are out of town, send for magistrates and have the necessary steps taken.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to President James Monroe, [Washington, D.C.], 13 June 1822., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Has received the President's message to Congress concerning internal improvements, "a question which very much divides the opinions of intelligent men;" "a general power over internal improvements, if to be exercised by the Union, would certainly be cumbersome to the government, & of no utility to the people. But to the extent you recommend, it would be productive of no mischief, and of great good;" he [John Marshall] despairs that such a measure will be adopted.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James [Markham] Marshall, Happy Creek, near Front Royal, Frederick County, 9 July 1822., 2 pages. Ph of ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
        Has found in the Journal of the House of Delegates that the bill for confiscating Lord Fairfax's estate passed in January 1786, but was defeated in the Senate; discusses the role of the Supreme Court in deciding cases relating to treaties; will not be at Happy Creek before 6 August; will also visit Cumberland, Mr. Colston's and maybe Bath.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.] to Benjamin Watkyns [sic] Leigh, Richmond, [Virginia], 2 February 1823., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Grants power of attorney to him [Benjamin Watkyns [sic] Leigh] to make or endorse any notes given by Edward Colston, James Marshall or James M[arkham] Marshall for the purpose of paying a debt to the Bank of the United States due from Nimrod Farrow or from the estate of Turner [?] Dixon.
      - [John Marshall], Washington, [D.C.], to Jaquelin B. Harrie, Richmond, Virginia, 8[?] March 1823., 1 page. ALS. Incomplete. Signature removed. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Asked Mr. [?] Williams about the information he [Jaquelin B. Harrie] desired; he [Williams] wrote that he gave his letter to the delegate from Florida, who has yet to answer it.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Warrenton, [Fauquier County, Virginia], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], 11 April 1823., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Discusses his trip from Richmond and the rainy weather; did not find Mr. [?] Skinker at home, so arrived last night at his friend's General [?] Blackwell's, who is almost blind; Tom [Thomas Marshall] was there earlier electioneering; the election will be closer than he [John Marshall] had originally thought.
      - Joseph Story, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 22 June 1823., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Met his son, Edward C[arrington] Marshall; introduced him to several gentlemen in Boston, and recommended him to the President of Harvard College; made arrangements for him [Edward Carrington Marshall] to live in Cambridge and to be tutored until rooms at the College are assigned after commencement; discusses his [Edward Carrington Marshall] expenses; takes great pleasure in aiding him in all measures; discusses his [John Marshall] latest decision on the Cashier of the Branch Bank of the United States; is anxious about the appointment of [Supreme Court] Judge [Henry B.] Livingston's successor.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 2 July 1823., 4 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Thanks him for his friendly attentions to his [John Marshall's] son, [Edward Carrington Marshall]; gives his opinion of the case of the Bank of the United States v. Dandridge; alarmed at the rumored successor of their "much lamented friend" [Supreme Court Justice Henry B. Livingston].
      - John Lowell, Roxbury, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 25 October 1823., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Discusses libels against his father, John Lowell, and against himself; encloses letters to editors printed in local papers in defense.
        Including NCls. 6 pages.
      - [John Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], to [John Lowell, Roxbury, Massachusetts], 6 November 1823., 3 pages. [DF] of AL. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Received his letters of 25 and 28 October and was astonished to learn that he feels he [John Marshall] deliberately and unnecessarily "altered expressions which would be construed into the imputation of a crime..., against a gentleman..."; there was no evidence in the cases decision that his [John Lowell] testimony was disregarded or discredited-- "the opinion speaks for itself."
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 9 December 1823., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Brother [Bushrod] Washington had to adjourn the court at Philadelphia because of his illness; discusses a case on his [John Marshall's] circuit concerning the American ship, Pilot, captured by pirates and later recaptured by a squadron under Commodore [David] Porter; comments upon the extreme bitterness of Mr. [John] Adams, whom he still respects, and the publication of some of his correspondence.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, [Washington, D.C.], 9 December 1823., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
        Received the President's message to Congress, and thanks him for his mark of polite attention; he [John Marshall] too thinks that "we cannot look on the present state of the world with indifference."
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to John Randolph, Washington, [D.C.], 17 January 1824., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Thanks him for the report of the Secretary of the Treasury.
        Original is located in the University of Virginia on deposit at
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 23 February 1824., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Was uneasy that she heard of his accident before his letter reached her; his fall has kept him from court longer than he had expected; feels pain only when he moves; doctors say he is mending faster than they had expected; is treated with a great deal of kindness and attention; wives of the cabinet members call on him; passes the long hours of the night by thinking of her and their early life together.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 23 March [1824?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Will soon return to Richmond by steamboat; makes arrangements to have his servant, Oby, meet him at the dock to carry his portmanteau; is not able to use his arm; was surprised to see John and Elizabeth [(Alexander) Marshall], who were in town because the boat on which they traveled was being repaired, and they were making their way to Baltimore by stage.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to "Nephew" Thomas G. Marshall, Taylorsville, Hanover County, [Virginia], 15 July 1824., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Missed seeing him at Hanover Court House on Monday, presumably because of the cloudiness of the weather; will be there next court day to meet him unless it is inconvenient, in which case he [Tom] should let him [John Marshall] know immediately.
        Original is located in the Virginia State Library, on deposit
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Peter S. Du Ponceau, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 17 July 1824., 2 pages. Pst of ALs. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Has just finished reading the copy of his "Dissertation on the Nature and Extent of the Jurisdiction of the Courts of the United States," which he sent to him [John Marshall]; thanks him for the flattering manner in which he discusses some of his [John Marshall] opinions.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, [Washington, D.C.], 13 December 1824., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Thanks for sending a copy of his message to Congress; regrets that he [Monroe] is retiring, but congratulates him on his presidency.
      - [John Marshall], Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 8 February 1825., 3 pages. AL. Signature missing. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Reached Washington yesterday and paid his accustomed visit to the President; he [John Marshall] occupies the same room as last year; neither Judge [William] Johnson nor [Joseph] Story has arrived, and [Thomas] Todd is close to death; the roads were so good for the winter, he was glad he did not take the steamboat; rode from Hanover Courthouse to Fredericksburg with a Mrs. (Booth) Stone; dined with his aunt [?] Keith on Sunday; his nephew, William Marshall, visited him on Saturday; hopes that Mr. [?] Picket has filled the ice house already.
        Including Pst of AL. 2 pages.
      - [John Marshall], Washington, [D.C.], to [James Markham Marshall, Happy Creek [?], Virginia], 14 February 1825., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Discusses presidential election of 1824; ascribes it to the letters of [?] Kremer and to Mr. [?] Vanraensaeller's reluctant last-minute vote for [John Quincy] Adams; speculates about the Cabinet; including Mr. [?] Crawford's refusal of the Treasury, and [Henry] Clay's rumored acceptance of the State Department.
      - [John Marshall], Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 27 February 1825., 3 pages. AL. Signature missing. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Has received letters from his son and from his nephew, George [?], and has learned of the marriage of his [John Marshall] nephew, Edward Colston, who has moved to Honeywood, [Berkeley County, Virginia]; asks her to inform Mr. [?] Cole that he [John Marshall] has received his new black suit, and that [George] Kremer will soon print "a most scurrilous piece of abuse against [Henry] Clay[an anonymous letter in the Columbia Observer accusing him of bargaining with John Quincy Adams to give his support in the presidential election in return for the office of Secretary of State]; her [Mary Willis Ambler Marshall] cousin, Mrs. [?] Walker, thanked him for his check and the subscription raised for her by the members of Congress.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to James Monroe, [n.p.], 7 March 1825., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
        Asks him to accept a copy of his [Marshall's] colonial history; congratulations him on the successful termination of his political career.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Edward Everett, Boston, Massachusetts], 3 May 1825., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
        Is much honored by his election to the Bunker Hill Monument Association and asks what his membership will entail.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, Oak Hill, Loudoun [County, Virginia], 13 July 1825., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
        Has received his letters and documents stating his [Monroe's] claims on the U.S.; expects that he [Monroe] will receive as much as has ever been allowed to others for similar services.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Susan Ledyard, New York, 6 November 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
        Thanks her for her letter recommending [?] Caldwell, but he has already pledged himself to another person seeking office.
      - John Sergeant, Philad[elphi]a, [Pennsylvania], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 6 December 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
        In response to his [John Marshall's] requests in his last letter, he [John Sergeant] is enclosing copies of Mr. [?] Giles' speech found in Dunlap and Claypoole's 16 December 1796 paper and in the Aurora of the 15th sources located at the [?] Library; and germane to his biography of Washington.
      - Legal brief of the case of Cooper and Gilliam v. Field et. al, a case involving the illegal sale of escaped salves, [co. 1825]., 2 pages. AD. (Box-folder 3:4)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1826., 13 items. (Box-folder 3:4-5)
        - Timothy Pickering, Salem, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], 17 January 1826., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)